Finding aid to Dorothy May Anderson papers CA.MS.00374
Smith College Archives
Dorothy May Anderson papers
1930-1993
Smith College Archives
Anderson, Dorothy May
CA.MS.00374
0.417 linear feet (1 container)
Dorothy May Anderson taught landscape design at Smith College and contributed to the redesign of the Smith campus prior to joining the war effort in 1943. Her papers contains questionnaires, course material, photographs, newspaper clippings, and correspondence related to Anderson's professional life.
Biographical / Historical
Dorothy May Anderson was born in 1903 in Colville, Washington. She was one of only two students to graduate from the landscape architecture program at the State College of Washington in 1926. After working in Seattle for several years under Fred Cole, an English landscape architect, in 1929 Anderson returned to school to study at the Cambridge School of Art and Landscape Architecture. At that time, the Cambridge School was the best landscape and architecture school for women in the country. Financial difficulty forced Anderson to intersperse terms with landscaping work with Ellen Shipman and Louise Payson in New York, but she graduated in 1933 with her thesis "A School of Horticulture for Women".
In 1933, she was hired as landscape design and planting design teacher at the Lowthorpe School in Groton Massachusetts and later became the co-director of the school. In 1935, Anderson was invited to teach and redesign the grounds of Smith College. In 1943, Anderson left Smith to help in the war effort, working for the OSS Cartography Division until the end of the war. With few opportunities available in the field of landscaping architecture after the war, Anderson continued to work for the OSS, State Department, and Foreign Services in Cairo and Paris. In 1954, she joined the CIA doing similar cartographic work in the United States.
In 1966, Anderson retired from her position in the CIA as editor-in-chief of geographic reports. In retirement, Anderson remained professionally active, doing freelance writing and editing. In 1980, she published Women, Design and the Cambridge School: A History of the Smith College Graduate School of Landscape Architecture and Architecture in Cambridge. She passed away in 1993 at the age of 90.
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown
Related Materials
For additional information about the Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture, see also RG 60. Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture Records, 1919-1986 and the HOLLIS catalog by Harvard University.
Scope and Contents
The Dorothy May Anderson papers contain questionnaires, course material, photographs, newspaper clippings, correspondence and other materials related to Anderson's professional life.
Architecture -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Massachusetts -- Cambridge.; Landscape architecture -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Massachusetts -- Cambridge.; World War, 1938-1945 -- Cartography.; Smith College - Photographs; photographs; architectural drawings; obituaries; Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture; Smith College -- History -- Sources.; Anderson, Dorothy May
- Assistant Professor of Landscape Architecture, 1935-1943 (Box 663, Folder 1)
- Obituaries, 1993 (Box 663, Folder 2)
- Course materials: Botany 36, 1935-1936 (Box 663, Folder 3)
- Photographs-Smith College, 1930-1940's (Box 663, Folder 4)
- Smith President's House Plan, 1936 (Box 663, Folder 5)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, A-Ba, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 6)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, Bi-Br, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 7)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, Bu-Com, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 8)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, Con-D, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 9)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, E-G, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 10)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, H-I, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 11)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, J-K, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 12)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, L, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 13)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, M-Pa, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 14)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, Po-R, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 15)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, S-St, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 16)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, Sw-Wh, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 17)
- ASLA Questionnaire to Cambridge School Graduates, Wi-Z, 1960's (Box 663, Folder 18)